Guide to the Victor Hugo Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Victor Hugo collection
1816-1876
GEN MSS 412
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.6
(2 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
Collection contains letters to and from Victor Hugo, as well as holographs of writings by Hugo. Correspondence includes letters to Hugo from Juliette Drouet, Aleksandr Herzen, comte Léopold Hugo, Jules Janin, Jean Toussaint Merle, and Jules Michelet. Letters from Hugo include letters to Laure Junot, duchesse d'Abrantès, A. de Beauchesne, Alexandre Dumas, and Almire Gandonnière. Writings contain holograph drafts of fragments of several works, including poems from Châtiments and Toute la lyre, fragments of chapters from L'Homme qui rit and Les Miserables, corrected proofs for several pages of Napoléon le petit, and a holograph of the play "Irtamène."
Hugo, Victor, 1802-1885
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Victor Hugo, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to November 1998 have been organized into three series. Series I, Jean Gaudon Collection, contains letters to Hugo and his wife, Adèle, from various individuals, as well as small holograph fragments of drafts of several of his works. Series II, Bronson Pinchot Collection, contains letters from Hugo to various people, letters to Hugo from Juliette Drouet, and several holographs by Hugo, mostly untitled. Series III, Materials from Other Sources, contains additional letters and writings by Hugo.
Authors, French -- 19th century; Authors; Abrantès, Laure Junot, duchesse d', 1784-1838; Beauchesne, A. de (Alcide), 1804-1873; Drouet, Juliette, 1806-1883; Dumas, Alexandre, 1802-1870; Gandonnière, Almire, 1813-1863; Herzen, Aleksandr, 1812-1870; Hugo, Léopold, comte, 1828-1895; Hugo, Victor, 1802-1885; Janin, Jules, 1804-1874; Merle, Jean Toussaint, 1785-1852; Michelet, Jules, 1798-1874
- Jean Gaudon Collection, 1832-1873; Series I; 0.2; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Purchased from Jean Gaudon on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1978
  - LETTERS FROM HUGO
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Regarding Hugo's failure to be elected to the Académie française
  - LETTERS TO HUGO
    - Aubert, ----, 1841 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ballanche, [Pierre Simon], 1842 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Barbier, [Auguste], 1859 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Beauchesne, A. de (Alcide), 1845 Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bonnelly, A., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cornélie, ----, 1873 Jul 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Crestadoro, Andrea, 1861 Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Destrem, Jean, 1873 Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - [Dorval, Marie], [1832?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dufour, Albert, 1872 Aug 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Esquivos, Pancrasse, 1851 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Forget, J. C., 1864 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - [Foucher, Pierre], [1845 Feb 28?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Gonzales, Emmanuel, [1843] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Guiraud, Alexandre, 1840 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Herzen, Aleksandr, 1857 Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Hugo, Léopold, comte (nephew), 1860 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Janin, Jules Gabriel, 1856 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Joffroy, J. H., 1873 Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Lassailly, Charles, 1840 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Lavaneau, M[?], 1842 Jul 9 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lefebvre, Gilbert, 1873 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Le Marchand, E[?], 1872 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Martha, Félix, 1841 Jun 30 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes: Holograph poem in Hugo's hand
    - Merle, M. (Jean Toussaint), 1841 [Jan 8] (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Michelet, Jules, 1870 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Pongerville, ----, [1841 Jan 7] (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - E. R., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Roger, Jean-François, 1834 Apr 25 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Rougier, Mme ----, 1872 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Terrier, Dr. ----, 1860 Nov 18 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Weill, Alexandre, 1847 Jan 18 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Unidentified, [1851?] Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - LETTERS TO ADELE HUGO
    - Lacombe, Francis, 1851 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - WRITINGS BY HUGO
    - "A Juvénal," poem from Châtiments (VI, 13), holograph fragment, [1853?] (Box 1, Folder 37)
      On envelope dated 27 January 1853
    - "L'Ame à la poursuite du vrai," poem from L'Art d'être grand père (XVIII, 5), holograph (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Amy Robsart, holograph cover for the manuscript, 1864 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - "L'Empereur s'amuse," poem from Châtiments (III, 10), holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
      On back of letter signed "Duriez" dated 15 November 1857[?]
    - "L'Expiation," poem from Châtiments (V, 13), holograph drafts of sections I, II, IV and VII (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Holograph drafts of several poems from Châtiments, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
      On back of official form from the Dead Letter Office of Jersey to Hugo, dated 30 November 1852
      Includes: Fragments from "A l'obéissance passive" (II, 7), "Cette nuit-là" (I, 5), "Apothéose," "Joyeuse vie" (III, 1), "On est Tibère..." (V, 6), "Applaudissement" (VI, 16), "Force des Choses" (VII, 12), and notes from other works, possibly Théâtre en liberté
    - L'Homme qui rit, holograph draft of part of one chapter (VII, 4), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Les Misérables, holograph draft of part of one chapter (V, 6, 2), [1861?] (Box 1, Folder 44)
      On envelope dated 10 April 1861
    - Nouveaux Châtiments, holograph fragment, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Théâtre en liberté, holograph fragment, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - "Umbra," poem from Toute la Lyre (III, 45), holograph fragment, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Unidentified holograph fragments related to Hugo's time in Jersey and his experience with spiritualism (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Unidentified poem, holograph fragment, ca. 1846 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Bronson Pinchot Collection, 1828-1876; Series II; 0.3; (.75 box)
  Gift of Bronson Pinchot (Yale Class of 1981), 1996; Purchased from Sotheby Co., 1994-1995, from the collection of Bronson Pinchot
  - LETTERS FROM HUGO
    - Abrantès, Laure Junot, duchesse d', n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Baze, Jean-Didier, [1876] May 17 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Beauchesne, A. de (Alcide), [n.y.] Feb 14 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Bertin, Armand, 1846 [Feb 15] (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Briseaux, Auguste, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Bryan, William A., 1870 Jun 29 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Buloz, François, [1842], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Cressonnois, J., 1862 Feb 12 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Crestadoro, Andrea, 1861 [Sep 20] (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - David, ----, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Denis, Achille, [1859] Oct 16 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Dumas, Alexandre, [1867] Jun 17 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Gandonniere, Almire (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Hugo[?], Charles, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Jouslin de la Salle, M. ---- (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Landolphe, P. F., [1852] Sep 19 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Langlé, Ferdinand, 1845 Apr 20 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Laurent-Pinchat, Léon, 1853 Aug 7 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Meurice, Paul, 1869 Oct 12 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Noël, Alphonse Léon, [n.y.] Feb-Dec (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Pavie, Victor, 1828 Oct 30 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Robelin, Charles, 1847 Jul 8 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - [Solitis, Marie de], 1854 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Théâtre Victor Hugo, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - "Aux femmes de Guernesey," in the hand of Julie Chenay, 1870 Jul 22 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - To his son, [1843] May 22 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Unidentified doctor, [n.y.] Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Unidentified Justice of the Peace, [1848] Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Unidentified woman, [1868] May 8 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Unidentified woman, [n.y.] May 16 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Unidentified, presenting a song, [n.y.] Sep (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Unidentified, [1830?] Sep 9 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Unidentified, 1855 Jun 30 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Unidentified, 1870 Dec 13 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Unidentified, [n.y.] May 26 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Unidentified, [n.y.] Aug 19 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - LETTERS TO HUGO
    - Drouet, Juliette, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - WRITINGS BY HUGO
    - Napoléon le Petit, corrected proofs of the first 16 pages, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - "Ordre à suivre," holograph poem, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Untitled holograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Untitled holograph about political figures from Henry VIII to Louis Napoleon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Untitled holograph poem, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Untitled holograph poem on verso of drawing of a soldier in a café, entitled "Garde National de Paris" signed "Par Philipotteaux", n.d.
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Empty paper wrapper entitled "Choses personelles - Notes pour des éclaircissements ou faits qui me concernant", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Envelope with holograph notes and shopping list, [1883?] (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Receipt to M. Renduel, 1836 Dec 31 (Box 2, Folder 94)
- Materials from Other Sources, 1816-1871; Series III; 0.1; (.25 box)
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders
  - LETTERS FROM HUGO
    - Achard, Amédée, 1845 Apr 22 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Guiraud, Alexandre, 1835 Dec 27 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Hugo, Charles, 1859 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - du Meril, P[?], [n.y.] Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Noël, Alphonse Léon, 1830 Oct 4 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Stevens, M. ----, [ca. 1851-70?] (Box 2, Folder 100)
      In the hand of Juliette Drouet, signed by Hugo
    - Unidentified, 1871 Nov 27 (Box 2, Folder 101)
      Acc #: 550722-b
    - Unidentified, [n.y.] Jul 5 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - WRITINGS BY HUGO
    - Irtamène, holograph play, 1816 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Notebook with holograph notes and drawings, regarding a trip through France, 1835 Aug (Box 2, Folder 104)
      Includes: 2 poems published in Les Chants du crépuscule
- Oversize, n.d.
  - Untitled holograph poem on verso of drawing of a soldier in a café (in Series II), n.d. (Box bsd, folder 105)